Okay בוקר טוב. boker tov.
Today's דף, daf, at least the דף daf we're up to, is
י"ז. yud zayin. Today's דף daf is actually י"ח, yud chet, but
we're on י"ז. yud zayin.
And we are picking up with, in the middle-sized lines here,
we are actually four lines before the lines get their widest. The
line starts with the word בית רבי. Beis Rebbi. Okay, so two
words before that: שפחה של בית רבי מאי. Shivchah shel Beis Rebbi
mai.
So we're dealing with different interesting stories here about נידוי. niduy. So
we just had one about a rabbi who had a bad reputation.
Turned out it was to do with sort of sexual improprieties, and
a whole question about do you respond to it or not respond
to it. So as we said yesterday, sadly the more things change,
the more they remain the same. And now in the context of
that discussion, the גמרא Gemara mentioned a נידוי niduy that was placed
by רבי Rebbi's maidservant. So the גמרא Gemara is now going to
ask about what the story was with that. So it says the
following: שפחה של בית רבי מאי? Shivchah shel Beis Rebbi mai? What
was the story of the maidservant of רבי Rebbi's household?
אמתא דבי רבי, Amsah d'bei Rebbi, the maidservant of רבי Rebbi's household,
חזיתא לההוא גברא דהוה מחי לבנו הגדול. chazeisa l'hahu gavra d'hava machi
livno hagadol.
Saw a certain person that was hitting his son who was already
an adult.
And of course corporal punishment was a regular part of child-rearing in
those days. But here the problem was that the child was already
no longer a child. אמרה ליה, Amra lei, so she said, ליהוי
ההוא גברא בשמתא. l'havei hahu gavra b'shamsa. That person should be in
a state of שמתא. shamsa. דקעבר משום d'ka avar mishum ולפני עור
לא תתן מכשול. v'lifnei iveir lo sitein michshol.
He's transgressing putting a stumbling block before the blind. Why? דתניא, D'tanya,
as it says in a ברייתא, Baraisa, ולפני עור לא תתן מכשול,
v'lifnei iveir lo sitein michshol, דמכה לבנו הגדול הכתוב מדבר. d'makah livno
hagadol hakasuv m'dabeir. We're talking about an application of this verse, not
the only meaning of the verse, the application would be somebody who
hits their adult child, because that person is no longer in a
position that they will just accept that type of a punishment,
but rather will, could rebel against it and could lead to sin.
What type of sin? Maybe he could smite the parent, maybe he
could just in general lead to a rejection of authority and lead
to pushing the person more on the bad path that they're already
on, that was the reason for that punishment. So of course there's
a question here, fascinating question in the פוסקים, poskim, which is how
literally to take this גמרא. Gemara. What are the parameters of ולפני
עור לא תתן מכשול? v'lifnei iveir lo sitein michshol? So in halakhic,
in normal halakhic discourse ולפני עור לא תתן מכשול v'lifnei iveir lo
sitein michshol is defined in very narrow terms in terms of being,
transgressing the biblical prohibition. One for example basic criterion is what the
גמרא Gemara calls תרי עברי דנהרא, trei avra d'nahara, that it's only
if the person could not have sinned without your assistance. So if
you're on two different sides of a river and they want you
to hand them the טרף treif food, and there's no way they
could get to that טרף treif food without you handing it to
them and them meeting you halfway across the river, their hand stretched
out, so only because of you could they sin. Without that they
couldn't. That's לפני עור. lifnei iveir. For cases where otherwise they could
have sinned even if you're to some degree assisting them would not
be. And certainly a case like this where the person isn't even
in the process to do a thing, it's just that the type
of behavior you're doing could
possibly put them on a wrong path. So in general there's an
assumption that this is not meant in a strictly halakhic way, that
it's talking about the value, the problem of לפני עור lifnei iveir
of leading somebody into stumbling is here, but not necessarily the technical
עבירה. aveira. But anyway it is interesting because this does get discussed
in the halakhic literature about is this really a transgression of לפני
עור lifnei iveir in the technical halakhic sense. But anyway basically what's
fascinating is, and we could take a moment to reflect on it
as for all of us who have dealt with being told by
other people how we are or not parenting our children correctly,
we tend not to appreciate that type of interference when people are
telling us about how we should be parenting our children. So anyway,
and here's what's fascinating is, that here she is, she sees somebody,
doesn't appreciate the way he's parenting, and puts him in a
נידוי niduy because thinks that it's really going to lead to something
disastrous. And the גמרא Gemara actually says that was a meaningful נידוי.
niduy. Now what's also important about this is, that until now we've
really only seen one type of a person put somebody in נידוי,
niduy, which has been who? חכמים, Chakhamim, right? And that led to
even the statement at the top of this דף, daf, or the
focus on the idea of being מנדה לכבודו, menadeh l'khvodo, a very
sense of like subjective נידוי. niduy. My honor
has been offended and therefore it's not a universal נידוי. niduy. It
doesn't impact on other people, right? It's only me or... you know
my students, but certainly my רבי Rebbe wouldn't have to abide by
that נידוי niduy because it's about, not about a broader objective problem,
but, you know, my honor. Here you have רבי'ס Rebbe's maidservant putting
somebody in נידוי, niduy, which means, which gets us really to more
of the more general class of נידוי, niduy, it's non-subjective, the objective.
Somebody's actually doing something that's objectively wrong. And the interesting thing is
that, okay fine, doing something objectively wrong, so the נידוי niduy there
would not, would apply to everyone, but you still might think that
that, that נידוי niduy would have to be imposed upon by some
type of a rabbinic authority. And the fascinating thing we're finding out
here is not, is that it can be imposed upon by anyone,
right? רבי'ס Rebbe's maidservant sees this wrong behavior, and this is something
that she can say this נידוי niduy and that becomes a binding,
a binding נידוי niduy for everyone. So it creates this very funny
type of a society where anybody sees somebody doing something objectionable and
decides to put somebody in נידוי. niduy. Now we had a story,
I think, I forget where we're up to, we had or we're
going to have a story where, you know, basically you can come
to a rabbi and clarify, was that a legitimate נידוי? niduy? That
person just put me in נידוי, niduy, does it, did that, was
that really legitimate? You know, so you still might need somebody to
ascertain whether it was justified and therefore binding or not justified. But
still it becomes a quite fascinating and I would say in certain
ways disturbing type of a societal dynamics where people can be putting
one another like just in נידוי niduy based on things that they
observe. Now, it also gets to a question of like what types
of behavior, right? Oh, I don't like the way you're acting, I
think you're going to cause your son to sin, נידוי. niduy. Like
anytime I see you doing something, you know, objectionable I can put
you in נידוי. niduy. So we read the other day, you know,
רמב"ם Rambam lists twenty-four things that he got by collecting different instances
in the גמרא, Gemara, but one thing to note, and I'm not
exactly sure how this fits into it, is that it's not any
type of transgressive or objectionable behavior. A lot of it particularly is
rooted in things that are like מזלזל, mezalzel, you know, show a
disregard and a contempt for הלכה, halacha, halachic authority, rabbinic authority, rabbis,
you know, simple transgression, which is not a, which is not a
demonstration of contempt, is not a basis for נידוי. niduy. But still,
you know, some case like this certainly makes us ask, yes.
Well, another possibility is that maybe רבי'ס שפחה Rebbi's shifcha, was actually,
had the status of a חכמה. chachama.
Oh, maybe, yeah, well we do have fascinating stories about her and
about her knowledge of like, of a lot of like obscure rabbinic
terms, and a lot, right? It is true. So maybe, or you
know, maybe either because of her own knowledge or because of her
situatedness in רבי'ס Rebbe's household, you know, she had a certain status
to impose the נידוי. niduy. It's a good question, yeah. Yes.
Just a clarification, so the things that give rise to a person
being in the category of נידוי niduy
are things that must like show contempt for social norms, the authority
of the court, or whatever. Right.
And the, and the result is that they're supposed to adjust their
behavior. That whole list of things that we read yesterday.
Right, mostly it's on them. There is some things on everybody else
like don't stand, sit in their ארבע אמות, arba amot, you know,
you know, don't, you know, but mostly it's behavior they have to
adopt on themselves.
I like the word intentional contempt, because somebody who's already shown contempt
for the court is not going to comply with the punishment.
Now what's the enforcement then? Well, so after a person, if a
person, you know, does not, either does not change their practice after
being in נידוי niduy or does not abide by the נידוי, niduy,
then you up it to חרם. cherem. And חרם cherem actually is
much more broader societal, like nobody does business with this person, you
know.
But what happens, but what happens when you don't change your clothes?
Right, so that's what I'm saying. That would then lead to the
next step, state, which would be חרם. cherem. And חרם cherem is
something that, whether, whether, whether the person is doing it or not.
The נידוי niduy basically is a threat.
It's never an end.
What do
you mean?
I mean, it's like putting somebody on probation before you expel someone,
right? You know, but the probation can have rules of how you,
new things you're going to do now because you're on probation.
I'm trying to distinguish between corrective behavior and ritualized behavior. It's
very hard to imagine, or at least for me it's hard to
imagine, that they would do this, this thing reflecting contempt, right,
adopt the ritualized practice of showing, of, maybe, maybe, maybe that's it,
that it's supposed to be you have to ritualize your action. It
doesn't really change your behavior, you have to take on this ritualized
piece that shows contrition.
No, because the גמרא Gemara says that all, all the whole stories
we have before and that we generally have by the נידוי niduy
is that the נידוי niduy is released once the objectionable behavior has
changed. If you basically, you know, showed contempt to a rabbi, you
have to make up with the rabbi in order for the נידוי
niduy to be released.
But can you imagine a circumstance where the ritualized behavior is an
end?
Yeah, because people here are basically assumed to be fundamentally, you know,
respectful and invested in the society and its authority structures, and they
just had individual... acts that stepped over the line. But if you
want to be back in the good graces of society and you're
not fundamentally stepping out of the society, then you're going to want
to abide by these procedures.
That makes sense. So then, if you choose to rehabilitate, right, and
do the right thing, then you don't have to do this ritualization.
So that's what the discussion that came up before. If somebody rehabilitates
before the period of the נידוי nidui is over, can we release
the נידוי nidui at, you know, early? And the basic answer was
yes, we can, and I think we're going to see more of
that coming up. So, yeah. It does raise a good question, like
why would anybody ever endure the נידוי nidui for the entire period?
Like either, you know, if you're going to change, you should, right,
but sometimes people are a little, you know, right,
or you're going to continue to,
yeah I know, but you know, sometimes they put people in, reporters
who won't reveal their sources in jail for contempt of court and
they stay the whole period and they're stubborn.
Right, but that's what I'm asking. Right. Like the people come to
your house and rip your clothes, so now you're wearing ripped clothes.
Yeah, it does seem that you have to actually do it yourself
for most of the behaviors. Okay, so but it, yeah, you're right,
I mean it's really understanding like the nature of the societal dynamics
at least that allow for like almost the self-enforcement of the נידוי.
nidui. Okay, so now let's take a look, the next story. It
says like this. It says,
ריש לקיש, Reish Lakish, last of the narrow lines, and now we're
going to get some of these issues where they're going to, people
are going to put one another in נידוי nidui and it's going
to have to be essentially arbitrated. So let's take a look. ריש
לקיש הוי מנטר פרדיסא, Reish Lakish havei minater pardisa, Reish Lakish was
watching a orchard. אתא ההוא גברא וקאכיל תאני, Ata hahu gavra veka'achil
te'inei,
so a certain person came along and was eating figs from the
orchard. רמא ביה קלא, Rama beih kala, he yelled at him. He
said, stop eating my figs! ולא אשגח ביה, Velo ashgach beih, the
guy ignored him. אמר, Amar, so Reish Lakish said, ליהוי ההוא גברא
בשמתא, Leihavei hahu gavra beshamta, that person who's now just picking figs
and eating my figs should be in a נידוי. nidui. Again.
What, Reish Lakish had
the power to do that? Exactly. Again, though, it's notice that it's
somebody who's just doing an עבירה, aveira, like, you know, now again,
in both cases maybe it's an עבירה aveira that's not just an
עבירה aveira like, you know, doing something wrong on שבת, Shabbat, it's
an עבירה aveira that has certain societal implications, you know, breaking boundaries,
you know, in the sense of, you know, not treating other people's
property correctly, the way the person was trying to remonstrate his son,
but nevertheless, it's an עבירה aveira and you put somebody in נידוי.
nidui. You don't like this thing you're seeing. So he put him
in נידוי. nidui. אמר ליה, Amar leih, so the guy said back
to him, אדרבה, Adaraba, no, the opposite! ליהוי ההוא גברא בשמתא, Leihavei
hahu gavra beshamta, you should be in a נידוי, nidui, you know,
for putting me in נידוי. nidui. Why? אי ממונא נתחייבתי לך, Ei
mamona nitchayavti lach, just because I owe you money, נידוי מי נתחייבתי
לך, nidui mi nitchayavti lach, since when does that deserving of נידוי?
nidui? Now again, which again raises the question, right? Okay, what do
you mean money? It's not like you haven't been paying up a
debt. You stole from him. But let's see where the story goes.
אתו לבי מדרשא, Atu lvei midrasha, they came to the בית מדרש.
Beit Medrash. אמרו ליה, Amru leih, and they said to ריש לקיש,
Reish Lakish, or ריש לקיש Reish Lakish came to the בית מדרש,
Beit Medrash, שלו נידוי, Shelo nidui, what he did is binding, שלך
אינו נידוי, Shelach eino nidui, what you did is not binding. So
here's a great story, the rabbi's נידוי nidui isn't legitimate and this
person's נידוי nidui is. Now again, fascinating, like what did ריש לקיש
Reish Lakish do that was wrong? Okay, he put him in נידוי,
nidui, it wasn't deserving, but this guy, he's a גנב. ganav. So
I mean, if you look at תוספות, Tosafot, תוספות Tosafot is very
bothered with this, and if you look at תוספות, Tosafot, he says,
נידוי מי נתחייבתי לך, nidui mi nitchayavti lach, he says, אף על
פי שמשמתינן בעבור
ממון, Af al pi shemshamtenan ba'avur mamon,
like somebody, you know, is not coming to a court on a
monetary issue, you put them in נידוי nidui and that's a monetary
issue. הני מילי ממון, Hani milei mammon, אית לומר דהיה לו לקרוא
אותו לבית דין תחילה, it lomar dehaya lo likro oto leveit din
techila, שמה יפרע, shema yifra, you don't stam straight put somebody in
a נידוי. nidui. You go through the normal court system. You know,
by straight putting him in a נידוי, nidui, if it's a בין
אדם לחברו bein adam lachavero issue, you're also undermining the authority of
the court system. That's not how we deal with these types of
cases. So that's fascinating. That helps explain it, right? It's not every
עבירה aveira you put somebody in נידוי. nidui. Maybe I did something
wrong, but you deserve to be in נידוי nidui because you're trying
to short-circuit the court system. And then he says, ועוד דבית דין
נמי צר שהיה להם, Ve'od deveit din nami tzar shehaya lahem, and
then there's a whole period of waiting, you don't stam put somebody
in נידוי nidui right away. And then, but because this issue is
so troubling to תוספות, Tosafot, he suggests a, you know, very, an
אוקימתא, okimta, like a, a framing of this to make it less
problematic. If you look like the fourth, last four lines of תוספות,
Tosafot, ובשם רבינו תם שמעתי שהיו רגילים באותו מקום שאוכלים באילנות ונותנים
דמים. Uveshem Rabbeinu Tam shamati shehayu regilim be'oto makom she'ochlim be'ilanot venotenim
damim. והתם לא הוו עברי על הגזל.
Vehatam lo havu avri
al hagezel. Okay,
so maybe in that place it was acceptable, you can eat off
of people's trees as long as you pay them afterwards. So then,
right, ריש לקיש Reish Lakish was really overreacting. But the third answer
is much more interesting, right? Just because somebody does something wrong doesn't
mean you have a right to put them in נידוי, nidui, and
in a way his נידוי nidui was more problematic because it undermines
the normal court system.
Talking about עביד איניש דינא
לנפשיה.
avid inish dina
linafsheih. Well, right, which was an earlier line
of the דף. daf. Exactly. So, okay, so let's take a look.
ומאי תקנתיה? Umai taknateih? And now here David getting back to your,
to your question. So how are you now going to fix it?
Now that you, ריש לקיש, Reish Lakish, are in נידוי. nidui. זיל
לגביה דלישרי לך. Zil legabeih delishrei lach. So go to him to
get him to release you. You have to make up to the
person that you offended, and that person... Exactly. So okay, let's take
a look. ומאי תקנתיה, Umai takantei, and now here, David, getting back
to your question, so how are you now going to fix it?
Now that you, ריש לקיש, Resh Lakish, are in נידוי? nidui? זיל
לגבי דלישרי לך. Zil legabei delishrei lach. So go to him to
get him to release you. You have to make up to the
person that you offended, and that person can release you from this
state of נידוי. nidui. So he says לא ידעינא ליה, lo yadeina
lei, I don't know who that person was, it was some random
person off the street. So אמר ליה amar lei זיל לגבי נשיא
דלישרי לך. zil legabei nasi delishrei lach. Oh,
you can go to the נשיא, nasi, he'll release you. דתניא, detanya,
we learned in a ברייתא, braita, נידוהו ואינו יודע מי נידוהו, niduho
ve'eino yodeia mi niduho,
if somebody put you in נידוי nidui and you don't know who,
ילך אצל נשיא ויתיר לו נידויו. yelech etzel nasi veyatir lo niduyo.
You go to the נשיא nasi and the נשיא nasi will release
you, sort of
representing rabbinic authority or representing sort of political and societal authority which
has a lot to do this. Again, notice by the way the
nature of the נידוי nidui is the personal stake of the person
who put you into נידוי, nidui, right? And again that makes it
highly personal as opposed to like the רבי'ס, Rebbe's the שפחה shifcha
of רבי Rebbi story, right? So was this an idea, how would
we have framed why ריש לקיש Resh Lakish was a נידוי? nidui?
Because he was פוגע pogei'a in this person's כבוד? kvod? So it
was the same way that a רב rav could be מנדה לכבודו?
menadeh lichvodo? So then you have an idea that everybody has כבוד,
kvod, even a non-רב. rav. Is that it? What's the personal role
that this person plays? When the person who was hitting his son
was put in נידוי nidui by רבי'ס Rebbi's, שפחה, shifcha did he
have to release him from it? Or she was just, she's not
a party, she was just a witness, right? So it's quite fascinating
again that very subjective category of נידוי nidui where the person who
puts you is considered to be a party to the נידוי, nidui,
the offended party and the one that therefore is going to release
you. That's not every category of נידוי nidui presumably, but that certainly
is some of them.
And then the corollary question is from whence does this authority derive?
Is it actually the social authority that individuals can invoke when they've
been offended, or is it actually each individual has authority and it's
agglomerated or conglomerate, whatever the right word is, but in any case.
Interesting, right?
And that social question, and the other point about the נשיא nasi
which relates, wasn't exactly the point you were saying, but you know,
is it the issue of honor of the תורה Torah and like,
you know, rabbinic כבוד, kvod, or is it just every individual? Is
the נשיא'ס nasi's role here as the head rabbi or as the
head, you know, as the political head, right? Because the נשיא nasi
sort of embodies both, right? So it's interesting here the role of
the נשיא nasi in this because we have shifted from the כבוד
הרב kvod harav to a כבוד kvod of a of a layperson.
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara continues. אמר רב הונא, amar Rav
Huna, so says רב הונא, Rav Huna, באושה התקינו, be'Usha hitkinu, אב
בית דין שסרח אין מנדין אותו. av beit din shesarach ein menadin
oto. So here again we get to this, you know, problematics about
the about a rabbinic leader, a תורה Torah leader that and whether
he's put in נידוי nidui and on the one hand trying to
protect his honor, on the other hand the חילול השם chillul Hashem
and the way in which it undermines תורה Torah honor if people
can act in certain ways without, you know, without censure. So if
a אב בית דין, av beit din, right, which is second to
the נשיא, nasi, סרח, sarach, you know, literally stenches, spoils, acts, you
know, goes off the דרך, derech, אין מנדין אותו, ein menadin oto,
you don't put him in נידוי. nidui. אלא אומר לו, ela omer
lo, you say to him הכבד ושב בביתך, hikaved veshev beveitecha, you
know, sort of take
either take keep yourself weightily or you know, take the weight of
this or כבוד, kvod, respect your honor, you know, consider your honor
and go sit in your house. So you basically try to have
a private conversation, you know, it's so funny again the ways these
things still happen. Like, you know, they find out that a rabbi
is involved in, you know, cases of sexual abuse. So some people
say, well, you know, first let's just talk to the rabbi and
try to persuade them to change their behavior and to, you know,
maybe to retire, to do something else. We don't want to, you
know, disrespect him and actually publicly shame him by bringing this out,
you know. That really works a lot of the time. So anyway,
so the גמרא Gemara says, so first you try to say, look,
let's try to do this on the quiet, you know. Consider your
honor. I mean, there's actually was a case in Israel that people
might be aware of which was exactly this story, you know, that
a whole body of rabbis, you know, looked into the case and
realized that the person actually was had done a lot of really
bad stuff and rather than bringing it to the public, initially tried
to get the person in through private conversations to, you know, to
leave his position and so on. So anyway, so that's what you
say to him, הכבד hikaved
where were we? וחזור
וסרח. vechazor vesarach.
If he repeats and does, you know, and does these bad acts,
מנדין אותו. menadin oto.
Then, at the second stage, you put him in נידוי nidui מפני
חילול השם, mipnei chillul Hashem, because otherwise, you know, again the worst
is that you're seen to be condoning this type of a behavior
from a rabbinic authority and that obviously makes it all that much
worse. ופליגא דריש לקיש, uphliga deResh Lakish, and this argues on ריש
לקיש. Resh Lakish. דאמר ריש לקיש, de'amar Resh Lakish, תלמיד חכם שסרח
אין מנדין אותו בפרהסיא. talmid chacham shesarach ein menadin oto befarhesya.
You're not do it in public. Maybe he was scarred from his
previous state of being נידוי. nidui-ed. But anyway, אין מנדין אותו בפרהסיא,
ein menadin oto befarhesya, שנאמר, shene'emar, presumably never, even if he did
continues on this bad path, וכשלת היום וכשל גם נביא עמך לילה.
vechashalta hayom vechashal gam navi imcha layla.
If you stumble today, the prophet will stumble with you as well
at night. So what does that mean? כסהו כלילה. kaseihu kalayla. If
he's like a prophet, a religious authority, then you have to cover
it up like the night. So whatever ways you deal with dealing
with it, it should not be in public. You know, again, that's
the concern. Do people wind up thinking worse of the תורה Torah
because they see the public shaming of somebody of a תורה Torah
authority who has acted in the following way? Or, you know, but
if it's, if you assume the issue's going to come out eventually
anyway, better to make it public and to respond rather than to
be involved in the cover-up. So that's all, you know, that's, again,
the types of, like I said, the more things change, the more
they stay the same.
So, מר זוטרא חסידה, כי מחייב צורבא מרבנן שמתא, Mar Zutra Chasida
ki michayav tzurba merabbanan shamta, so מר זוטרא Mar Zutra the חסיד,
Chasid, when the—when a member of the rabbinic colleague—colleague, like a צורבא
מרבנן tzurba merabbanan is higher than just רבנן, rabbanan, which is like
one of the more rabbinic students. This is somebody who's already sort
of, he's not yet a רב, rav, like in the sense of
the full סמיכה, semicha, but he's one of, you know, he's a
member of the college. So when he was obligated in שמתא, shamta,
ברישא משמית נפשיה והדר משמית לדידיה. beresha mashmis nafsheh vehadar mashmis ledideh.
So first he would put himself in חרם cherem and then he'd
put the guy in חרם. cherem. So that's like the story about
the spilling of the wine on the table so that the guests
feel comfortable.
Before I'm going to put you in חרם, cherem, I'll put myself
in חרם. cherem. Like, what did he do to deserve חרם? cherem?
But this way, it somehow is not seen as a disgracing of
the other person if he's doing it to himself.
So, you know, תוספות, Tosafot, if you look at תוספות Tosafot tries
to deal with this, and תוספות Tosafot says משמית נפשיה משום צער
שצריך לנדות תלמיד חכם, mashmis nafsheh mishum tza'ar shetzarich lenadot talmid chacham,
which is interesting because, you know, we dealt with the parallels of
נידוי niduy to הנהגי אבילות. hinhagei avelut. And by אבילות, avelut, you
have the sense of צער, tza'ar, a suffering of pain, of anguish.
By נידוי, niduy, you have fundamentally the practices that set a person
apart from society. And by אבילות, avelut, we discussed, how do you
see some of these practices? Do you see these practices also that
the אבל avel is pulling, you know, him/her—himself out of society, you
know, that whole week of שבעה shiva and so on, and not
engaging in society? Or do you see the practices that are—at least
the practices that are similar to those of נידוי niduy as the
same effect of נידוי? niduy? Or are they different? Are they more
expressions of צער tza'ar and there's something different that just happens to
parallel? תוספות Tosafot here is doing the reverse. He's saying maybe an
aspect of נידוי niduy could be an expression of צער. tza'ar. So
the guy didn't do anything wrong by putting the other rabbi into
נידוי, niduy, but he felt so terrible about it and he wanted
a means of expressing how devastated he felt, so he himself adopted
the practices of נידוי niduy to express that. But again, it's fascinating
because נידוי niduy always accompanied a sense of censure, not just an
expression of צער, tza'ar, not
just a state of אבילות avelut like I was saying before. Right,
I know, but I'm saying, but it makes it a practice—if you
could call it a practice of אבילות, avelut, it's one thing, but
it's a practice—it's a state. It's not just he adopted the practices
of נידוי. niduy. He put himself in נידוי. niduy. It's a state
of נידוי. niduy. So תוספות Tosafot's second answer is אינמי שיהא זכור
להתיר, inami sheyehei zachur lehatir, so that he would—because we'll see the
end of the story about that he wouldn't want this status to
remain, so to remember he had to take care of that guy's
status, he put himself in the same status. So let's just finish
that story. So it says,
where was it? מר זוטרא חסידה Mar Zutra Chasida, כי מחייב צורבא
מרבנן שמתא, ki michayav tzurba merabbanan shamta, והדר משמית לדידיה. ve-hadar mashmis
ledideh. כי הוי עייל באושפיזיה, ki havei ayel b'ushpizeih,
and then when he got to his inn, so, you know, a
few hours later, שרי ליה לנפשיה, sharei leh lenafsheh, he was מתיר
matir his own נידוי, niduy, because he put himself in נידוי, niduy,
so he could be מתיר matir his own
נידוי, niduy, והדר שרי ליה לדידיה, ve-hadar sharei leh ledideh, he released
the other person from the נידוי. niduy. So תוספות Tosafot sees that
the reason he put himself was as a reminder, in order, you
know, if he had had his iPhone, he would have just plugged
it in there, but this way, he reminded himself, so he took
care of it that way. Again, fascinating that A, we saw before
cases of putting oneself in—in case of נזיפה, nezifa, right, a status
of נזיפה, nezifa, but that's after the rabbi already expressed the displeasure
and then you just sort of, you know, translated that into reality.
Here, it's not נזיפה, nezifa, it's actual נידוי. niduy. You're putting yourself
into it, and even when you didn't do anything wrong. Right? So
it's a whole new fascinating little phenomenon, yes.
Do you see a connection between this and the cities of refuge
and כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, so he's held responsible for the people,
and here his disciple did something wrong, so he may be holding
himself a little bit responsible?
Oh, oh, interesting. Maybe putting himself in נידוי niduy because he has—he's
sharing in the responsibility.
Right. I mean, it doesn't specifically frame it as a student of
his, but maybe you're right. Maybe he sort of sees a responsibility
for what every—what everybody else is doing. Right. That's an interesting question.
That's interesting. Okay,
זאת, zot, yeah. I just—reminds me of, it's only a slight digression.
They tell a story about רב חיים, Rav Chaim, you know, רב
חיים Rav Chaim from בריסק, Brisk, that, you know, like, obviously a
genius at a young age, he was like five years old or
something. And so, the רבי Rebbe of the town, who—or his רבי,
Rebbe, who had been learning, you know, teaching him, when—when his רבי'ס
Rebbe's רבי Rebbe came to, you know, visit בריסק, Brisk, so he
wanted to show off this child prodigy he was teaching. So he
brought him in front of the, you know, his own רבי, Rebbe,
and the רבי Rebbe asked him some, like, you know, hard question
on the גמרא, Gemara, and he answered it brilliantly, and he said,
"Wonderful," and gave him as a little reward... before he gave him
an apple. So he took a bite of the apple without making
a ברכה. Bracha.
So his, so the, so you know, so the visiting רבי Rebbe
said to רב חיים Rav Chaim and he said מסתמא mistemah he
learned to take a bite, you know, to eat apples without making
a ברכה Bracha from his רבי. Rebbe. And so רב חיים Rav
Chaim said and מסתמא mistemah he learned from his רבי! Rebbe!
All right.
All right. So moving on.
But anyway, I was reminded of that. Shared responsibility for how everybody
is acting. Anyway, all right, moving on.
Okay, where are we?
So the גמרא Gemara says like this. אמר רב פפא, Amar Rav
Pappa, תיתי לי, taysi li, רב פפא Rav Pappa said, "It should
come to me," meaning I deserve
credit, דלא שמיתי צורבא מרבנן מעולם, delo shemisi tzurva merabbanan me'olam, that
I never had to or I never did put any member of
the college,
of the rabbinic college into נידוי. niddui. אלא כי מיחייב צורבא מרבנן
שמתא, Ela ki mechayiv tzurva merabbanan shamta, that doesn't mean everybody is
always acting correctly. When somebody does something that's deserving of
שמתא, shamta, היכי עביד, heichi avid, what do I do? כי הא
דבמערבא, ki ha dema'arava, I do like they do
in ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. מינו אנגידא דצורבא מרבנן, minu angida detzurva
merabbanan, ולא מינו אשמתא. velo minu ashamta. They actually take, you know,
get together a בית דין, Beit Din, מינו, minu, like they take
a counting, a vote, whatever to give somebody lashes, but not to
put somebody in שמתא. shamta. So actually it is better to use
corporal punishment, and we talked, remember before we were talking about when
we discussed some of the sources of נידוי niddui and then we
went on to say and how do you know you can smite
somebody and kill somebody and hit somebody and put them in the
stockades and whatever? So he actually said that's better than putting somebody
in חרם. cherem. Now that sounds bizarre to us, but I actually
understand it. Right? A state of societal censure, right, is something and
you're, certainly that lasts for thirty days, right, that could be much
more harmful, you know, much more powerful than just a type of
a physical punishment which takes a period of time and then you're
done with it. I mean, I'm not saying putting in the stockades,
that's also the same type of societal shaming and censure, but you
know, if it's a, if it's a brief period of physical punishment
that might be a lot less hurtful to the person and their
status than having been in a state of נידוי. niddui. So it's
quite fascinating that he sees like this is the better thing and
the more respectful thing to do towards a תלמיד חכם Talmid Chacham
is this type of physical punishment rather than נידוי. niddui.
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says מאי שמתא, mai shamta, what
does this, the meaning of the word שמתא, shamta, which is like
נידוי niddui sounds, you know, is Hebrew, שמתא's shamta Aramaic, so what's
the etymology, asks the גמרא. Gemara. אמר רב, Amar Rav, שם מיתה,
sham mita,
there there is death. So again talking about this sense of, you
know, about one's shaming and societal status, a type of a social
death. ושמואל אמר, uShmuel amar, שממה יהיה, shmama yiheye, he'll
be in a state of desolation. ומהני ביה כטיחא בתנורא, umahani beih
keticha betanura,
and now the גמרא Gemara speaks about I, you know, you could
understand it to be this sort of sense of, again, of shame
and societal status, but I think it also speaks about it in
a more metaphysical terms that the state of putting somebody in שמתא
shamta is like the greasing they do of the walls of the
oven which, you know, basically like keeps the tastes in, locks in
the tastes. So you put somebody in נידוי niddui like that, you
know, the sort of the, the punishment, you know, the metaphysical punishment
gets sort of stays in the person, locks in. So it's very
harsh.
So, ופליגא דריש לקיש, upliga deResh Lakish, this argues on ריש לקיש.
Resh Lakish. דאמר ריש לקיש, De'amar Resh Lakish, כשם שנכנסת במאתים וארבעים
ושמונה איברים, keshem shenichneset bematayim ve'arba'im ushmonah evarim, the same way this
state of שמתא shamta enters into a person's two hundred and forty-eight
limbs, כך כשהיא יוצאת, kach kshehi yotza, when it goes out and
when a person is released from the נידוי, niddui, יוצאה ממאתים וארבעים
ושמונה איברים, yotza mimatayim ve'arba'im ushmonah evarim, it leaves, completely departs the
person. So we're clearly talking about some, again, you could talk about
some societal, you know, vestige of it, but it seems like we're
talking more at the metaphysical realm. דכתיב, dechtiv, as the verse says,
כשם שנכנסת דכתיב, keshem shenichneset dechtiv, how do you know when it
goes in? It says והיתה העיר חרם. Vehayeta ha'ir cherem. The word
city should be חרם. cherem. חרם cherem is the worst, right, that's
the next stage after a נידוי. niddui. That's a concept you already
have in the תורה, Torah, under the ban. But חרם cherem בגימטריא
be'gematria במאתים וארבעים ושמונה הוי, be'matayim ve'arba'im ushmonah havei, right, חרם cherem
look at that, it's two hundred and forty-eight, exactly the number of
limbs that the חז"ל Chazal say that a person has. כשהיא יוצאת,
kshehi yotza, how do you know when it leaves? It leaves in
the entirety of a person's body. דכתיב, dechtiv, ברוגז רחם תזכור, berogez
racheim tizkor, even in anger remember your compassion.
רחם racheim בגימטריא הכי הוי, be'gematria hachi havei, so the same word
of חרם cherem is the word of רחם. racheim. It's brilliant, right?
So the same thing of putting the person into the ban, right,
then there's the compassion and the person is released from it and
that also completely reverses the effect. But it's not surprising, I mean
the גמרא Gemara does not exactly spell out the ritual that accompanied
it, although we heard before about the blowing of the שופר, shofar,
we're going to hear about that again. You know, I'm sure people
have heard, I mean, for most people like I, you know, I
don't know, you know, stories of putting someone in חרם, cherem, certainly
they tell, you know, about how they put Spinoza in חרם, cherem,
you know, with the candles and the dark lights and the. and
the darkening and the שופר shofar so it's not surprising that there
would accompany to the idea of what the impact of חרם cherem
is not just the societal realities that result but some type of
a spiritual metaphysical way in which this
person is transformed and impacted and that certainly seems to be reflected
here yes
חרם cherem and רחם racham aren't just the same גימטריה gematria they're
the same
letters right exactly it's exactly so one does wonder if there's something
going on there beyond this sort of story like whether
that seems to be a little bit more than a coincidence okay
so now the גמרא Gemara is continuing אמר רב יוסף Amar Rav
Yosef so שדי שמתא shadi shamta now talking about the metaphysical impact
let's listen to this
story שדי שמתא אגנובתא דכלבא shadi shamta agunavta d'kalba he threw a
נידוי nidduy on the tail of a dog ואיהו דידיה עבדא v'ihu
d'idei avda and the
נידוי nidduy will take care of itself will sort of act on
its own what does that mean putting a dog into נידוי nidduy
so דהוא כלבא d'ahu kalba there was a dog דהוה
אכיל מסאני דרבנן d'hava achil masney d'rabbanan it was eating the shoes
of the rabbis it was chewing on their shoes there you go
again disrespecting the honor of the rabbis it should know whose shoes
it's eating ולא מיקדיע מנו v'lo mikyadia manu they didn't know whose
dog it was so they couldn't talk to the
owner ושמתו ליה v'shamtu lei and they put the dog into
נידוי nidduy אתלי בה נורא דגנובתיה itlibey nura d'gunavtei a fire caught
hold of the dog's
tail ואכלתיה v'achaltei and it burned up the dog so if Rivka
עליה השלום aleha hashalom were here she would remind us of the
problems of צער בעלי חיים tzaar baalei chayim in all these stories
which is true it's like no concern here for the dog anyway
but here you see this idea of the metaphysical power of נידוי
nidduy which the גמרא Gemara is now bringing into the conversation ההוא
אלמא hahu alma there was a certain very powerful person that was
causing anguish להוא צורבא מרבנן lahu tzurba m'rabbanan that was causing anguish
to one of the rabbis of the college אתא לקמיה דרב יוסף
ata l'kamei d'rav yosef he came to Rav Yosef and said what
should I do about this guy אמר ליה זיל שמתיה amar lei
zil shamtei he said go put him into נידוי nidduy אמר ליה
מסתפינא מיניה amar lei mistafina minei I'm afraid of him and then
I'll put him into
נידוי nidduy he's the guy that has all the societal power right
what is he going to do to me as a result אמר
ליה amar lei so he said to him שקיל פתיחא shkiley pticha
take a like a piece of paper a parchment that you have
written out basically the נידוי nidduy on שקיל פתיחא ליה shkiley pticha
lei write out a little write it out don't announce it don't
maybe blow שופרות shofars do a big announcement just write out the
נידוי nidduy כל שכן דמסתפינא מיניה kol shekain d'mistafina minei how's that
going to help surely I'll be afraid of him maybe it'll make
it even more public I'll put it in writing I don't get
what you want me to do אמר ליה שקליה amar lei shaklei
take this paper where you wrote out the נידוי nidduy אחסייה בכדא
achsei b'kada put it into an earthenware
vessel okay ואחסייה בקברי v'achsei b'kivrei and go ahead
and put it in a like in a cemetery וקרי ביה אלפא
שיפורי דארבעים יומין v'karay bei alfa shipurey d'arbaim yomin and go blow
in it a thousand שופר shofar blasts over forty days talking about
some type of a
superstitious metaphysical ritual that's going on here
עבד הכי avid hachi he did this פקע כדא paka kada at
the end of doing all these שופר shofar blasts inside
of the vessel the vessel finally exploded ומית אלמא u'meis alma and
the guy died when the vessel exploded the person died so we
have really caught a transforming in these last few passages the power
of נידוי nidduy as a tool within society of societal censure to
having something of this type of metaphysical
power what's
that a curse
it's a yeah but it's not just a curse the way you
curse somebody and they get embarrassed or whatever it has real power
right it's a
real
curse it's voodoo right okay anyway so I don't know what to
say it's not
what look one also imagines right and I guess this story is
indicative of that that what
happens how much did Spinoza's being put in חרם cherem affect Spinoza's
life like what do you do when nobody cares about the fact
that you put them into
חרם cherem right right so what happens when the societal impact is
not having its being effective because of the in this case cause
this person was a very powerful person in society it wouldn't have
made a difference to him he's not going to practice it nobody's
going to care nobody's going to stop doing business with this guy
right so when these things stop having their the intended power that
they were meant to
have the emphasis in these last few stories is shifting to this
type of metaphysical power that's being attributed to it
yes isn't it simply reading that the חכם chacham is afraid that
he's
just going to beat him up yeah you mean not just that
he won't practice it yeah okay but here
he's saying that this this and he has more social power and
he has more power in the society right right.
Oh, you mean just a thug. Right. Right. So maybe other, right,
right, it could be. It could be. So maybe that, yeah, you're
right, you're right, maybe I'm trying to reframe it too much. But
okay, that's possible. Nevertheless, it certainly relates to the fact that the
נידוי nidui is not always effective in the ways it was meant
to be effective, even if what you're reading, which is probably the
simpler one, is just because a person is afraid to impose it.
Okay, but that could be.
Yes. כלבא אמבי עלמא kalba ambei alma are examples of the rabbis
not having, no longer are they trying to correct someone's behavior. They
can't speak to a dog, and they can't have any effect on
this guy. So, rather than it being an expression of their power,
it's become an expression of their disempowerment, which makes them uncomfortable, I'm
assuming. And so now we have to go to
this becomes an, you know,
metaphysical power as absolutely a reflection of their lack of power.
I think that's very, that's very well said. Thank you. Yes, exactly.
Exactly that. So, let's take a look at now the גמרא Gemara
because it deals with the שופר shofar blowing, which has now been
mentioned, which was alluded to before. מאי שיפורי? Mai shipuri? So what
is the idea of a שופר? shofar? So now a little play
on the word שופר, shofar, like with the word שמתא, shamta, שנפרעין
ממנו, she-nifra-in mimenu,
that ultimately this person's sins will be, you know, will, you know,
will be exacted from him. Again, presumably meaning at some spiritual plane,
not necessarily, you know, in terms of, and the same way, notice
also the דרשה drasha on the word שמתא shamta was after the
discussion about how it makes the stuff stick in you and it
doesn't go out of you. So all these like דרשות, drashot, right,
it makes sense as well. You're giving symbolic significance to it when
it's losing its real practical teeth. Right? So we're now saying, oh
look, the word שמתא shamta means it'll insert, it'll cause מיתה mita
to be present. The word שופר shofar means that you'll be, punishment
will be exacted. You don't have to make דרשות drashos if the
stuff has a very clearly... somebody is thrown in jail, you don't
have to say what's the symbolism of the word jail, right? So
you have to make these דרשות drashos of the symbolism if some
of the impact is, I think, being weakened. Okay. מאי תברא? Mai
tavra? And what's the word תברא, tavra, which is like תרועה, truah,
a broken sound? So אמר רב יצחק בריה דרב יהודה, Amar Rav
Yitzchak breih de-Rav Yehuda, תברי בתי רמי, tavri batei ramei, it'll cause
high houses to fall down. דתניא, De-tanya, we learned in a ברייתא,
braita, אמר רבן שמעון בן גמליאל, Amar Rabban Shimon Ben Gamliel, כל
מקום שנתנו חכמים עיניהם, kol makom she-natnu chachamim enayhem, whenever the rabbis
gave their eyes against somebody, like they gave that, you know, evil,
evil look, the evil eye on someone, או מיתה או עוני, o
mita o oni, either the person died or he became poor. And
there you go again, Lynn, exactly the point you're saying, right? You
have to say that because they're not actually being effective in any,
like, very concrete real terms that are observable. Oh, it's they are
going to have this power and they're going to be able through
their gaze to cause death, to cause poverty, and so on. So
it's quite fascinating how the last section, the last like fifteen lines
after a good two pages on נידוי, nidui, like the thing we're
left with at the end, on the one hand, you can say,
talks about the immense power of the נידוי, nidui, right, the way
it has this tremendous metaphysical power and all these things, but it
also speaks, as, you know, as Lynn very articulately said, about a
disempowerment, about its lack of real-world impact that it's being shifted, you
know, to these types of issues. As we do know, though, you
know, certainly in the Middle Ages, חרם cherem and נידוי nidui was
used as a means of, you know, controlling people and so on,
but it was not always effective and they dealt with similar types
of problems. Okay, so now we move on to the next part
of the
משנה. Mishna. והנזיר והמצורע מטומאתו לטהרתו. Veha-Nazir veha-Metzora mitumato letaharato. Other people
that can do, clean their clothes and get a haircut on חול
המועד Chol HaMoed is a, or here we're dealing with getting a
haircut, is a נזיר Nazir and a מצורע Metzora that are now
becoming טהור. tahor. So they could not have done this earlier because
of their status, and now they're able, so they're able to get
a haircut on חול המועד. Chol HaMoed. So the גמרא Gemara says
like this, בעי מיניה רב ירמיה מרב זירא, Ba'ei minei Rav Yirmiya
me-Rav Zeira, Rav Yirmiya asked Rav Zeira, בשלא היה להם פנאי או
דילמא אף על פי שהיה להם פנאי? beshelo haya lahem pnai o
dilma af al pi shehaya lahem pnai? Once we put these into
a special category, right, it's like the reverse of another question, right?
The other question is, let's say somebody isn't in a special category,
but the גמרא Gemara asks, or just was looking at or trying
to find a lost object, right? Didn't have any time, you know,
do we allow that person to shave on חול המועד Chol HaMoed
because okay, they're not in a special category but the reality is
they didn't have a chance beforehand? And the basic answer was no,
we don't, right, we have to have formal categories. So here we're
sort of asking the flip side of that question. A person is
in the formal category, but they but they don't deserve an exception.
Yes, they became טהור, tahor, but you know what? They became טהור
tahor a day before יום טוב. Yom Tov. Could have taken care
of it before יום טוב. Yom Tov. So maybe they shouldn't get
the allowance to do it on יום טוב. Yom Tov. So let's
take a look. אמר ליה, Amar leh, he
said, תנינא, tannina, we talked, כל אלו שאמרו מותרים לגלח במועד, kol
elu she-amru mutarim legaleach ba-moed, all those that we said can get
a haircut on the חול המועד, Chol HaMoed, בשלא היה להם פנאי,
beshelo haya lahem pnai, it's only when they didn't have a chance,
when they became טהור tahor on when their status changed on the
יום טוב, Yom Tov, on חול המועד. Chol HaMoed. אבל היה להם
פנאי... Aval haya lahem pnai... if they had a chance prior, אסורין
asurin and they're forbidden. Now but that's as a general rule. Okay,
so that would be like the guy that was יצא מבית האסורין.
yatza mibeis ha'asurin. He got released from prison if he got released
a day before יום טוב, Yom Tov, set your haircut a day
before יום טוב. Yom Tov. That's this first set of cases in
the משנה. Mishna. אבל, Aval, but, in the case of, I'm sorry,
but נזיר nazir and מצורע, metzora, but in the case of נזיר
nazir and מצורע, metzora, אף על פי שהיה להם פנאי, af al
pi she'hayo lahem p'nai, even if they had a chance, מותרין. mutarin.
Why? What makes them special if other people, it's only when they
didn't have a chance? Why? שלא ישהו קרבנותיהם, shelo yish'hu korbanoseihem, they
should not postpone their קרבנות. korbanos. What does that mean? Normally, ironically,
because normally a concern of postponing your קרבנות korbanos is, is that
if we let you do it on חול המועד, Chol HaMoed, you're
going to wait to חול המועד Chol HaMoed because anyway you have
to be עולי לרגל, olei l'regel, you'll be in ירושלים, Yerushalayim, why
go ahead and bring your קרבן korban a week before יום טוב?
Yom Tov? You know, you're going to let me take care of
it on יום טוב. Yom Tov. So a concern actually of why
we should forbid things on חול המועד Chol HaMoed so you don't
wait. But here the גמרא Gemara is saying the concern is the
opposite. Here you were, you're the נזיר, nazir, you know what, you
should have taken care of it yesterday ערב הרגל, erev ha'regel, you
didn't, it happened, right? What's going to be the effect if we
tell you don't take care of it now on חול המועד? Chol
HaMoed? So if you're not going to do the ritual of shaving
the hair, right,
then you're not going to bring your קרבן korban until after because
you that you well now there's a whole interesting הלכה halacha question,
does it have to precede the קרבן? korban? תוספות Tosafos says it
doesn't really strictly have to, you could do the קרבן korban without
that, but in the normal way in which things are done, the
process is first you do the shaving of the hair, then you
do the קרבן, korban, then you use the hair to burn underneath
the שלמים, shlamim, the תורה Torah describes the whole thing, how you
take the hair, you throw it under the pot that's cooking the
שלמים shlamim and so on. So therefore if we say no, it's
going to make things—it's going to create another problem. Now look, this
is what people say about how can you tell me not to
shave on חול המועד, Chol HaMoed, not to get a haircut on
חול המועד? Chol HaMoed? The whole purpose was I shouldn't enter into
the רגל regel looking disheveled, now you're going to tell me don't
take care of it and I'm going to be disheveled during the
רגל, regel, right? Which is by the way, you know, I'd remind
you that there are many פוסקים poskim that say that nowadays that
people, well let's say men, you know, shave daily, if a person
actually does shave daily, so then you know the whole status is
it's not like a special case, the whole reality is that even
when you take care of it ערב רגל erev regel you have
to take care of it on the רגל regel and therefore you
can shave on חול המועד. Chol HaMoed. That's certainly what my practice
is and not to do something would be a problem of disrespecting
כבוד הרגל. kavod ha'regel. But anyway, in general, let's put that aside,
in cases where you should have done it once and then it
wouldn't have had to be done again and you were negligent or
you didn't do it, you know, some people will object and say,
but okay, you're making the problem worse because now you're you're forcing
me to continue to be disrespectful of the רגל. regel. But there
you could say okay, that's the cost. The cost of creating the
incentive for people to do it beforehand is that
sometimes you know there will be less כבוד הרגל kavod ha'regel as
a result. But here what the גמרא Gemara is saying is there's
an additional cost, in addition to the כבוד הרגל kavod ha'regel cost,
you're also paying in the sense that you're postponing ending this process
of נזיר, nazir, מצורע, metzora, you're postponing the קרבנות korbanos and we're
not prepared to pay that additional cost. And therefore we're going to
say that at least if you did not have a chance you
can take care of it that, I'm sorry, even if you did
have a chance you can take care of it on the רגל
regel so you don't have to pay that additional cost. Okay, so
now the גמרא Gemara continues. תניא, Tanya, we taught
in a ברייתא, Braisa, two other people that are allowed to do
it on the רגל regel that are not in our
משנה, Mishna, הכהן והאבל מותרין בגילוח. hakohen v'ha'avel mutarin b'giluach. Now אבל
avel is interesting because אבל avel is always been there in the
background, but it wasn't mentioned in our משנה. Mishna. So an אבל
avel we sort of understand,
somebody's אבלות avelus ended when the רגל regel came and now they're
allowed to shave and get a haircut, right? So can they do
it on חול המועד Chol HaMoed if they didn't do it before
the רגל? regel? That we understand, they didn't really have a chance
before the רגל. regel. כהן Kohen is less clear. I'll just tell
you now, the גמרא Gemara will elaborate that כהן kohen is talking
about somebody who who was his משמר mishmar leading up to the
רגל. regel. And during their משמר, mishmar, they're also not allowed to
shave and get a haircut and launder for the similar, I mean
it's all ironic, right? They have to be more a little bit
more disheveled potentially during it so that they take care of it
ahead of time. But anyway, it's a similar type of a case
where they only become possible, it only becomes possible to do it
during, you know, during the רגל regel because they were the משמר
mishmar led up to the רגל. regel. So will they be allowed
to take care of it on חול המועד? Chol HaMoed? Let's take
a look.
הכהן והאבל מותרין בגילוח. hakohen v'ha'avel mutarin b'giluach. Now the גמרא Gemara
wants to understand this ברייתא. Braisa. האי אבל היכי דמי? Hai avel
heichi dami? What's the case of the אבל? avel? It's a more
straightforward case. אילימא שחל שמיני שלו בערב הרגל, Ileyma she'chal shmini shelo
b'erev ha'regel, if the eighth day of אבלות, avelus, right, because an
אבל avel cannot get a haircut or shave for all of שלשים.
shloshim. So in order for it to be possible, they have to
be out of שבעה shiva and the eighth day has to begin
ערב הרגל erev ha'regel for the רגל regel to negate שלשים shloshim
and that would allow them to get a haircut. So the simple
case is that that's what happened, day eight fell out ערב הרגל.
erev ha'regel.
So אילימא שחל שמיני שלו בערב הרגל, ileyma she'chal shmini shelo b'erev
ha'regel, איבעי ליה לגלוחי בערב הרגל, ibai lei l'giluchei b'erev ha'regel, so
why didn't you take care of it on ערב הרגל? erev ha'regel?
Because if the רגל regel is going to become because the הלכה
halacha is is that you could say, well, you know, the שלשים
Shloshim isn’t בטל batul until the רגל Regel comes, right? Until tomorrow.
But the הלכה Halacha actually is that if the רגל Regel is
going to be מבטל mevatel the שלשים, Shloshim, then because that’s sort
of like anticipated and in the offing, that that allows the person
to, you know, bathe and launder and take a haircut or whatever
לכבוד הרגל likhvod ha-Regel the day before. So that’s actually the הלכה,
Halacha, right, that if the רגל Regel is coming to מבטל שלשים,
mevatel Shloshim? you can actually take care of those things ערב הרגל
Erev ha-Regel in order for כבוד הרגל. kavod ha-Regel. So why didn't
you do it? You had a chance. אלא
שחל שמיני שלו להיות בשבת ערב הרגל. Ella she-chal shemini shelo lihyot
be-Shabbat Erev ha-Regel. Oh, must have been that day eight was שבת
Shabbat and the יום טוב Yom Tov began on Sunday. So in
that case, you would not have been allowed, you didn't have the
opportunity to get the haircut on ערב הרגל, Erev ha-Regel, it was
שבת. Shabbat. So איבעי ליה לגלחו בערב שבת. Iba'ei lei le-galchu be-Erev
Shabbat. So the גמרא Gemara says, so what? In that case, you're
even allowed to take care of it
on Friday, even though it's day seven of the אבילות. aveilut. Why?
דאמר רב חסדא אמר רב עינא בר שילא, De-amar Rav Chisda amar
Rav Ina bar Shila, הלכה כאבא שאול. halacha ke-Abba Shaul. We rule
like אבא שאול Abba Shaul who says
that, you know, even when day seven falls out ערב הרגל, Erev
ha-Regel, because, you know, it's a whole tricky thing, right? If day
seven falls out ערב הרגל, Erev ha-Regel, so we say מקצת היום
ככולו. miktzat ha-yom ke-kulo. So the אבל aveil stops being נוהג שבעה
noheg shiva the beginning of day seven, right? So do we say
that because they've stopped the mourning of day seven, the rest of
day seven is already the beginning of שלשים? Shloshim, And therefore, since
רגל Regel will come the next day, right, that the רגל Regel
is מבטל שלשים? mevatel Shloshim. Or does שלשים Shloshim? in order to
have officially started essentially need its own day? You can't really use
this day seven to get double credit. Like, okay, it's counted as
the last day of שבעה, shiva, as a שבעה shiva day, and
it's counted the rest of שבעה shiva and it's also a שלשים
Shloshim day, so the person started שלשים Shloshim so that the רגל
Regel is מבטל. mevatel That's the debate of אבא שאול Abba Shaul
and the חכמים. Chachamim. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says and אבא
שאול Abba Shaul says you can get double credit, and if a
person's seventh day of אבילות aveilut falls out ערב הרגל, Erev ha-Regel,
then the רגל Regel is מבטל שלשים. mevatel Shloshim, So let's take
a look. So it says הלכה כאבא שאול. halacha ke-Abba Shaul. We
rule like אבא שאול. Abba Shaul. ומודים חכמים לאבא שאול, U-modim Chachamim
le-Abba Shaul, and the sages agree to אבא שאול Abba Shaul שחל
שמיני שלו להיות בשבת ערב הרגל, she-chal shemini shelo lihyot be-Shabbat Erev
ha-Regel, at least in the case where day eight was on שבת
ערב הרגל. Shabbat Erev ha-Regel. In that case, they agree שמותר לגלח
בערב שבת. she-mutar le-galeach be-Erev Shabbat. They'll allow the person to take
care of it on day seven, ערב שבת. Erev Shabbat. Okay, do
you understand? Because in that scenario, the fact that the eighth day
fell out ערב הרגל Erev ha-Regel means that the רגל Regel will
be מבטל שלשים, mevatel Shloshim. right, because day eight was ערב הרגל.
Erev ha-Regel. The only it's only a practical problem that there's no
opportunity on שבת, Shabbat, so there they'll say, we'll actually let you
do that during day seven because at least there's a reality that
the רגל Regel will be מבטל שלשים. mevatel Shloshim, If day seven
was ערב הרגל, Erev ha-Regel, then there's no ביטול bitul of שלשים,
Shloshim so they're not going to let you take care of your
shaving or whatever on that day. Okay, so anyway, so the גמרא
Gemara says whatever the scenario was, you could have done it before
the רגל Regel began. All right, so the גמרא Gemara says, לא
צריכא, lo tzericha, here's the case. Now you can't say, so whether
the שלשים Shloshim, began on so it has to be שלשים Shloshim
began ערב הרגל, Erev ha-Regel, whether that day was שבת Shabbat or
not שבת, Shabbat, the גמרא Gemara would have said there would have
been an opportunity to have taken care of it when you could
have either ערב הרגל Erev ha-Regel or ערב ערב הרגל. Erev Erev
ha-Regel. Now, if you'll say, well, maybe שלשים Shloshim didn't begin on
ערב הרגל, Erev ha-Regel, maybe the
שבעה, shiva, the רגל Regel came in the middle of שבעה, shiva,
well, then there's no opportunity to shave because the רגל Regel isn't
מבטל שלשים, mevatel Shloshim right? Your only opportunity to shave is if
the רגל Regel is מבטל. mevatel. So what's the scenario, says the
גמרא? Gemara?
If the שבעה shiva didn't finish beforehand, it's not going to be
מבטל שלשים mevatel Shloshim? and no opportunity to shave. If the שבעה
shiva did finish beforehand and the person was in שלשים Shloshim in
one of the other scenarios, then you're allowed to shave ערב הרגל.
Erev ha-Regel. So what's the case that you didn't have a chance?
So let's take a look. So the גמרא Gemara says, לא צריכא
שחל שביעי שלו להיות בשבת ערב הרגל. lo tzericha she-chal shevi'i shelo
lihyot be-Shabbat Erev ha-Regel.
The case is that day seven was שבת ערב הרגל. Shabbat Erev
ha-Regel. So, and according to אבא שאול, Abba Shaul, what would be
the story? Day seven is שבת ערב הרגל. Shabbat Erev ha-Regel. Is
the רגל Regel מבטל שלשים? mevatel Shloshim
Yes, because day seven counts both for the end of שבעה shiva
and the beginning of שלשים. Shloshim Can you get a haircut on
day seven? No. So what's the last opportunity you could have got
a haircut? On day six. Nobody will allow you to get a
haircut during the שבעה shiva itself. We might allow you to get
it on day eight when you're in the שלשים Shloshim. period and
the שלשים Shloshim is about to be מבטל mevatel. it. We might
even allow you on day seven because for day seven the person
has moved from שבעה shiva to שלשים Shloshim and the שלשים Shloshim
is going to and the רגל Regel is going to be מבטל
mevatel שלשים Shloshim and even the rabbis that normally don't do that
on day seven might in some cases allow you in order to
get ready for the רגל. Regel. But in all those cases there
is a way of looking at it that the person isn't during
שבעה. shiva. And since they're during their שלשים Shloshim and the שלשים
Shloshim is about to be מתבטל, mitbatel, we can allow them to
take care of it. But in this scenario, when day seven is
on שבת ערב הרגל, Shabbat Erev ha-Regel, the only opportunity is day
six and we're never going to allow it ממש mamash in the
middle
of
שבעה. shiva. Yeah. Right, or after the morning of day שבעה.
seven. Right. Already moved into שלשים. Shloshim. So if that seventh day
is an ערב הרגל, Erev HaRegel, then why isn't the רגל Regel
מבטל mevatel the שלשים? Shloshim?
It is, and a person can shave and whatever on that day.
But what if that day falls out on שבת? Shabbos? So the
only option is the אבל. Avel. Okay, so that's the scenario where
an אבל Avel is now allowed on the רגל Regel to do
it, but didn't have an opportunity beforehand. Okay, that's the אבל Avel
case. So now why did our משנה Mishnah not mention that case?
Why was that only in a ברייתא? Baraisa? So the גמרא Gemara
says like this: תנא ברא Tanna Bara סבר, savar, the outside תנא,
Tanna, the ברייתא Baraisa we just quoted holds, כסבר, Kasavar, דאמר d'amar
מקצת היום ככולו, Miktzas Hayom Kekulo, ויום שביעי לו כאן ולו כאן.
V'yom shevii lo kan u'lkan. That day seven is שבת, Shabbos, yes,
but שבת Shabbos will be מבטל mevatel the שלשים Shloshim because you
get double credit for day seven. And therefore, now during the רגל,
Regel, this person is out of their שלשים Shloshim and can shave.
וכיון דשבת הוי אונס, V'kivan d'Shabbos havei oness, and they couldn't have
taken care of it ערב ערב Erev Erev because it was שבת,
Shabbos, it was out of the person's hands, אנסו. Anusu.
And therefore you can take care of it, a person can take
care of it during the רגל. Regel. תנא דידן Tanna didan סבר,
savar, our תנא Tanna holds, לא כרבנן, lo ke-rabbanan, דאמרי לא אמרינן
מקצת היום ככולו, d'amri lo amrinan Miktzas Hayom Kekulo, that we don't
say day seven counts double. That the רגל Regel is only מבטל
mevatel שלשים Shloshim if day eight falls out before the רגל. Regel.
והאכתי לא שלם אבילות דשבעה, V'hakati lo shalem aveilus deshiva,
and the person didn't finish שבעה. Shiva. So even though the רגל
Regel came, that only stops שבעה, Shiva, the person is still in
שלשים. Shloshim. The person's still in שלשים, Shloshim, they can't shave regardless
of the רגל, Regel, they're still in שלשים. Shloshim. That's that case.
Okay, so that's that issue why it's in the ברייתא Baraisa and
not in our משנה, Mishnah, the scenario that day seven was שבת
Shabbos ערב הרגל. Erev HaRegel. האי כהן היכי דמי? Hai Kohen heyichi
dami? What's the case of a כהן Kohen mentioned in the
ברייתא? Baraisa? אילימא דשלים משמרתו Ileima deshalim mishmarto ערב הרגל, Erev HaRegel,
same question. If his משמרת, mishmereth, his round in the בית המקדש
Beis HaMikdash ended before the רגל Regel was up. Right?
The משמרת mishmereth always ends on שבת. Shabbos. So if שבת Shabbos
was ערב הרגל, Erev HaRegel, so איבעי ליה לגלוחי iba-i lei legiluhei
ערב הרגל. Erev HaRegel. Now you can't shave on שבת, Shabbos, right,
because they switch on שבת. Shabbos. But when we teach that a
כהן Kohen can't take a haircut during his משמר, mishmar, we say
he can't take it even on Thursday. Even though the משמר mishmar
only ends on שבת, Shabbos, he can't take it on Thursday לכבוד
שבת. Lichvod Shabbos. So if שבת Shabbos was ערב הרגל, Erev HaRegel,
so okay, so fine, שבת Shabbos is ערב הרגל, Erev HaRegel, but
take your haircut on Thursday or Friday. So big deal, what's the
problem? So the גמרא Gemara says,
לא צריכא דשלים משמרתו ברגל. lo tzericha deshalim mishmarto ba-Regel. Okay, fine.
So שבת Shabbos the week he was in, you know, the רגל
Regel fell out on a Thursday
and his shift went into the רגל. Regel. So he was only
free from his shift in the middle of the רגל, Regel, and
that's his opportunity to get a haircut, he couldn't have done it
beforehand. תנא דידן Tanna didan סבר, savar, our תנא Tanna holds, כיון
דתנן, kivan detnan, since we taught in the משנה, Mishnah, בשלש פרקים
בשנה היו כל המשמרות שוות, Beshalosh Perakim bashanah hayu kol hamishmaros shevos,
three times in the year all the משמרות mishmaros had equal opportunity
to serve in the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash and equal rights to
the קרבנות. korbanos. באמורי הרגלים, Be-emurei ha-regalim, the various parts of the
sacrifice, of the limbs of the, אמורי emurei normally means the parts
that are burnt on the altar, but here it also means the
parts that they get to eat, the meat that are brought on
the רגלים, regalim, ובחילוק לחם הפנים, uvichiluk lechem hapannim, and in the
division of the לחם הפנים lechem hapannim which is done on שבת.
Shabbos. Anyway, during the רגל Regel there's equal division of a lot
of the communal sacrifices. So therefore, even though his משמר mishmar ends
during חול המועד, Chol HaMoed, but כמאן דלא שלים משמרתו ברגל דמי.
keman delo shalim mishmarto ba-Regel dami. Right, he's not allowed to get
a haircut not because it's still חול המועד. Chol HaMoed. You know
why he can't get a haircut? Because it's still his משמר. mishmar.
So the normal argument was his משמר mishmar went into the רגל,
Regel, his משמר mishmar is now over during חול המועד, Chol HaMoed,
he didn't have a chance to shave beforehand, let's let him shave
on חול המועד. Chol HaMoed. But wait a minute, in the רגל
Regel all כהנים Kohanim are equally have an equal opportunity to work
in the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash and to have a portion of
the קרבנות. korbanos. So it's still considered to be an extension of
his משמר, mishmar, and therefore from the perspective of his משמר mishmar
he's not allowed, being in his משמר mishmar he's not allowed to
get a haircut. You can't shave during a משמר. mishmar. Right.
Okay. So תנא ברא Tanna Bara סבר, savar, that's what
our תנא Tanna says, that he did not have that as an
exception. And the other תנא Tanna holds, אף על גב דשייך בהנך
משמרות, af al gav deshayaich behanech mishmaros, even though he has a
portion with the other משמרות, mishmaros, but משמרתי, mishmartei, his real, you
know,
the specific obligation and his status specifically to be on duty, משלמא,
mi-ashlima, that was over, and now he is able to shave from
the משמר mishmar perspective, and since he didn't have a chance beforehand,
he's able to shave from the חול המועד Chol HaMoed perspective as
well.
Why can't you shave during a משמר? mishmar?
Same reason as חול המועד, Chol HaMoed, to take care of it
ahead of time. תנו רבנן, Tanna Rabbanan, כל אלו שאמרו מותרין לגלח
במועד, kol elu she-amru mutarin legaleach bamoed, מותרין לגלח בימי אבלם. mutarin
legaleach bimei evlam. Now all these people that have exceptions on חול
המועד Chol HaMoed have an exception for אבילות, aveilus, meaning let's say
somebody, now that's a little bit of... somebody got freed from prison
and didn't have a chance to shave and then they became an
אבל, Avel, right? So would they be allowed to shave? So it's
a little bit bizarre because, you know, רגל Regel you can anticipate.
So if you tell me I can't shave on the רגל, Regel,
it means I anticipate the רגל Regel and I'm going to take
care of it ahead of time. אבלות, Avelus, sometimes you can, but
obviously very often you can't anticipate. And therefore, what can I do
ahead of time? Number one. Number two is, you know, another way
of saying the same point is that the reason for this practice
during אבלות Avelus is not to ensure it gets taken care of
ahead of time. The reason is because it's an expression of אבלות.
Avelus. So by the רגל Regel where the whole point is to
ensure you take care of it ahead of time, we'll say if
you were unable to, we'll waive the issue, because the whole point
was to create an incentive, you know, and a pressure to do
it earlier. Here, it's to express the אבלות. Avelus. So why should
the fact that the person didn't have a chance beforehand have anything
to do with the need to be an expression of the אבלות?
Avelus? So that's so that's very strange. So let's see what the
גמרא Gemara does with this. So the first statement is מותר לגלח
בימי אבלו, Mutar l'galayach b'ymei evlo, but then the גמרא Gemara says
wait a minute we taught in the ברייתא Baraita אסור. Asur. It's
not an allowing. So here we're going to resolve the ברייתות Baraitas
and address the issue I just framed. אמר רב חסדא אמר רב
שילא Amar Rav Chisda Amar Rav Shila כי תניא הכא מותרים בשתקפו
אבליו. Ki tanya hacha mutarin b'shetakfu avelav. Now, the reason it's allowed
here is because of the burden. It's not like fundamentally the whole
point was to take care of it earlier. But here this person
just got freed from prison, so already has this long head of
hair, then became an אבל, Avel, right? And then let's say it's
actually a case over multiple אבלות. Aveluses. So he was an אבל
Avel for a while and then נעבעך Nebach another person died before
he had an opportunity to get a haircut from the first אבלות.
Avelus. So now it's just becoming so difficult and burdensome that we
make a special leniency. So it's not because the point was to
do it earlier. It's because this will be another reason that it's
just making this extremely burdensome and we will give him a leniency.
So the גמרא Gemara says one minute, if that's true that it
was multiple אבלות Aveluses that came one after another, מאי איריא כל
אלו שאמרו? Mai irya kol elu she'amru? Why did it have to
be a special case of let's say being freed from prison? אפילו
כל אדם נמי, Afilu kol adam nami, a normal person that has
a sequential series of אבלות Aveluses would have this leniency. דתניא D'tanya
we taught in the ברייתא Baraita תקפו אבלו Takfu avelo if, you
know, the אבלות Avelus came one after the other, זה אחר זה,
Zeh achar zeh, הכביד שערו Hichbid se'aro his hair gets heavy, מיקל
בתער Meikal b'ta'ar he can lighten it, you know, he can cut
some hair with a with a with a razor, ומכבס כסותו במים
U'michabes k'suto b'mayim and can launder his clothes with water. So there's
already a leniency. So the גמרא Gemara says, yeah, but that's not
going the full way. איתמר עלה Itmar alei it was said that
that leniency is limited. אמר רב חסדא בתער ולא במספרים, Amar Rav
Chisda: b'ta'ar v'lo b'misparayim, sure, but you can use a razor but
you don't use scissors, you don't do a full haircut. You just
do a lightening of the hair. במים ולא בנתר, B'mayim v'lo b'nester,
you can use water, you can't use soap detergent. So normally if
it's multiple things, we give a certain degree of leniency. If it's
the multiple things plus the guy had been in prison for the
last two months, right, so then we're going to let you give
a normal haircut, we'll let him get a normal type of a
laundering. Okay, so אמר Amar and the last thing we'll do for
today, אמר רב חסדא זאת אומרת, Amar Rav Chisda Zos omeret, by
the way, this whole discussion demonstrates that אבל אסור בתכבוסת. Avel asur
b'tichboset. Since we say in certain cases you can do, you know,
laundry, this shows that the normal rule is you can't do laundry.
Of course, like we said that a million times. So sometimes the
point is you can't even do laundry without detergent. Since you needed
a special leniency to do the laundry with water even without detergent,
it shows the general rule is that even without detergent an אבל
Avel is not allowed to do laundry. Okay, so we're a full
דף Daf behind. Tell.